Guide to the George Whitmore Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Whitmore papers
1959-1995
1967-1989
YCAL MSS 274
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.88
(21 boxes)
The George Whitmore Papers consists of the literary papers of the poet, playwright, critic, novelist, and freelance writer George Davis Whitmore. The collection primarily contains his writings and supporting research files, though a small amount of professional correspondence and a few personal papers are present.
Whitmore, George, 1945-1989
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Michael Cantor on the Ezra Pound Archive Fund, 1996.
The Whitmore archive was stored by Canter between Whitmore's death in 1989 and transfer of the archive to the library in 1996. According to Canter, Whitmore's "early Kaypro" computer was discarded in 1990 or 1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files are available through Access Services. Surrogates of all audio recordings are available within the collection.
Boxes 20-21: Restricted fragile material. Reference copies available. Consult access services for further information.
George D. Whitmore (1945-1989)
George Davis Whitmore was a poet, playwright, critic, novelist, and freelance writer, whose lifetime of publishing began with his essays appearing in school literary magazines and ended with his major volume on the AIDS epidemic. He was born in Denver, Colorado, on September 27, 1945, to Lowell and Irene Davis Whitmore. Raised in Denver, he received a BA degree in English and Theatre from MacMurray College in Jacksonville, Illinois, in 1967. Whitmore was awarded a Woodrow Wilson Fellowship and pursued graduate studies in the Theatre Department at Bennington College, Bennington, Vermont. He remained at the college from 1967 to 1968, after which he moved to New York.
Once in the city, Whitmore found employment as an editorial and administrative assistant at two non-profit agencies, Planned Parenthood (1968-1972) and the Citizens Housing and Planning Council of New York (1972-1981); both positions gave him experience in writing copy, reviewing books, and turning out concise feature articles under deadline. Concurrently, Whitmore maintained a parallel career as a freelance writer, reporter, and critic for several gay periodicals including The Body Politic, Christopher Street, Gay Sunshine, and Gaysweek, as well as serving as contributing editor and literary critic at the San Francisco Advocate from 1974 to 1976. In addition, he wrote on topics of interest to the gay community for other magazines such as the Soho Weekly News, Harper's Weekly, and the Washington Post Book World. His book-length study of Henry David Thoreau was published by the Gay Academic Union in 1977-1978.
Whitmore also worked in fiction throughout his life, composing poetry and short stories that were published in both gay and straight periodicals, as well as issued under his own imprint, the Free Milk Fund Press, which was headquartered in his Upper West Side apartment. He received a New York State CAPS grant for poetry in 1976, and regularly presented his poems at public readings during the 1970s and early 1980s. Three of Whitmore's plays were produced in New York: The Caseworker (1976), Two Plays for Three Women: Flight/The Legacy (1979), and The Rights (1980), and three of his novels were also published there: The Confessions of Danny Slocum (1980), Deep Dish (serialized between 1980 and 1982), and Nebraska (1987). The latter, loosely based on Whitmore's childhood memories, was developed from an earlier unproduced play and written during his residencies at the Edward Albee Foundation (1983) and the MacDowell Colony (1985). Whitmore was a member of a literary group known as the Violet Quill, whose seven authors, as men creating literature for men, are regarded as the strongest voices of the gay male experience in the post-Stonewall era. Christopher Cox, Robert Ferro, Michael Grumley, Andrew Holleran, Felice Picano, Edmund White, and Whitmore met several times in 1979, 1980, and 1981, to read aloud from and discuss their works in progress, as well as those by their friends. Also on their agenda were discussions of how they could work together to promote recognition, acceptance, and publication of gay literature beyond the boundaries of their own community.
In the 1980s, Whitmore worked as a freelance reporter and features writer for popular magazines and newspapers including Travel and Leisure, House and Garden, House Beautiful, and the New York Times; his specialty was covering people, places, and events connected with art, design, and architecture. At the same time, his personal and professional communities were rapidly being overtaken by the shadow of the AIDS epidemic, as gay male friends and colleagues around him began to sicken and die. Whitmore's response was perhaps his most important contribution to non-fiction literature: three interrelated articles and one book that focused on human face of AIDS. Relying on his reporting skills and journalism contacts, he fashioned the first article for a general public already frightened by rising morbidity statistics: "Reaching Out to Someone with AIDS," a profile of the daily life of an AIDS patient and his volunteer advocate, appeared in The New York Times Magazine on Sunday, May 19, 1985, some months before President Ronald Reagan publicly acknowledged the disease. A second article, "Someone Was Here," ran in GQ the next year. Whitmore reused the title for his 1988 book, Someone Was Here: Profiles in the AIDS Epidemic, which expanded on his Times article by looking at the lives of patients' families and medical professionals as well as the patients themselves, thereby emphasizing the toll of the disease on both the heterosexual and homosexual populations. The book's epilogue was published in advance in the January 31, 1988, issue of The New York Times Magazine. In that essay, "Bearing Witness," Whitmore revealed that he too was a victim of AIDS, having been diagnosed a year after the publication of his "Reaching Out" article. He was 43 years old when he died in New York on April 19, 1989, from AIDS-related complications.
Scope and Contents
The George Whitmore Papers consists of the literary papers of the poet, playwright, critic, novelist, and freelance writer George Davis Whitmore. The collection primarily contains his writings and supporting research files, although there is a small amount of professional correspondence and a few personal papers present. Whitmore's writings span his academic years through his career as a freelance journalist, but nearly half of the collection contains his creative writings, many of which were not published during his lifetime. Whitmore was a member of the Violet Quill group of gay male writers, and most of his literary works reflect his close connection with contemporary gay culture in tone and subject, particularly his AIDS-related writings.
With the exception of one letter from the author to his sister and one to his friend James Ross (Jay) Smith, the collection does not contain personal or family correspondence, health or financial files, daily planners, or any information related to Whitmore's successful human rights lawsuit against the Northern Dispensary. Therefore, the small group of journal entries in Series I are noteworthy for providing the collection's only window on Whitmore's daily activities and inner thoughts.
Among his literary contributions were extensive published interviews with authors William S. Burroughs, Martin Duberman, Tennessee Williams, and Edmund White, and the singing group Labelle (Patti LaBelle, Nona Hendryx, and Sarah Dash), in addition to AIDS patients and care givers. In his fiction and non-fiction work, Whitmore covered topics of relevance to the gay community, and the papers reveal his working methods and resources for his success in both genres.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series: I. Personal Papers (1966-1995); II. Writings: Fiction (1959-1989); III. Writings: Non-Fiction, General (before 1967-1988); IV. Writings on AIDS (1984-1989); V. Subject Files (1973-1988); VI. Electronic Files (1981-1986).
AIDS (Disease); American fiction -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Gay men -- Fiction; Gay men -- United States; Gay men's writings, American; Violet Quill (Group of writers); Dublin (Ireland) -- Description and travel; England -- Description and travel; Glasgow (Scotland) -- Description and travel; Ireland -- Description and travel; Diaries -- United States -- New York; Electronic documents; Guidebooks; Scripts (documents); Sound recordings; LGBTQ resource; Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997; Duberman, Martin B.; LaBelle, Patti; Sassoon, Sybil, 1894-1989; Thoreau, Henry David, 1817-1862; White, Edmund, 1940-; Whitmore, George, 1945-1989; Williams, Tennessee, 1911-1983; Labelle (Musical group); MacDowell Colony (Peterborough, N.H.)
- Personal Papers, 1966-1995; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains a collection of records documenting Whitmore's life: a few pieces of correspondence and photographs, some academic material, a short run of journals, and biographical material including interviews he gave and resumes he wrote. Parts of his academic career are covered by four undergraduate term papers and a set of instructors' reports from his time at Bennington College. AIDS material related to Whitmore's own health conditions is filed in this series, while that which he collected while writing his articles and books on the disease appear in Series IV. The Correspondence file has just a few letters; others can be found in both the folders of the various publications in Series III and in electronic form on several computer disks referenced throughout the finding aid. There are three folders of material related to the "Emma Morris Free Milk Fund," including some of their colorful silk-screened graphics; the Fund appears to have been a humorous club formed and promoted by Whitmore and his friends. Whitmore was awarded two residencies at the MacDowell Colony, in Peterborough, New Hampshire, and went there to write in the fall of 1985 and the spring of 1987. The folders for each visit include a set of snapshot photographs taken during his time at the retreat.
  The five folders of journals contain three blank books with manuscript notes as well as sheets of typescript notes detailing Whitmore's activities and inner thoughts, particularly during the months in 1985 when he was researching his article on AIDS for the New York Times. A folder of published interviews and profiles helps to flesh out the abstracts of Whitmore's career and death provided in the resumes and estate papers filed in this series. At the end of the series is a set of manuals and instructions for using Whitmore's Kaypro computer and WordStar software.
  The latest item in the collection is a letter filed with Whitmore's correspondence. Dated May 11, 1995, it is from David Bergman to Victor Bumbalo, Whitmore's literary executor. Berman worked with Bumbalo to publish some of Whitmore's writings in his anthology The Violet Quill Reader (1994).
  - Academic material
    - Records, 1966-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      Includes one issue of the Bennington College Quadrille
    - Research papers, before 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AIDS information, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Letters to Duncan Stalker are also available through Access Services: Disk #31, files STALKER, BURRELL, and CALKE.
    The letter to James Ross (Jay) Smith is also available through Access Services: Disk #48, file JAY.
    A letter to Whitmore's sister Mary Jo Hamel is available through Access Services: Disk #43, file JO.
    Additional letters to editors of Architectural Digest, House and Garden, Manhattan, Inc., New York Times, Pan Am Clipper, Travel & Leisure, and Vogue are available in electronic form through Access Services: Disk #43
    Contains letters to and from Peter Biskin, David Feinberg, Andrew Hodges, Duncan Stalker and James Ross (Jay) Smith. Also filed here is a letter from David Bergman to Victor Bumbalo. Additional letters to editors are filed in Series III.
  - Emma Morris Free Milk Fund, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - Estate documents, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Funeral arrangements, electronic file, 1988 Sep 12
    Available through Access Services: Disk #29, file WILL
  - Housing records, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Interviews and profiles of Whitmore, 1978-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes articles from The Advocate, Alternate, The Body Politic, Christopher Street, and Gotham
  - Journal, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Journal, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Journal, 1984 Oct-Nov (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Journal, 1984 Dec-1985 Sep (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Electronic files of journals dating from April 7 though September 30, 1985, are available through Access Services: Disk #47, in files titled by month and day.
  - Journal, England, 1985 Jul (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Electronic file also available through Access Services: Disk #47, files ENG1, ENG2, ENG3
  - MacDowell Colony residency, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Includes snapshot photographs
  - MacDowell Colony residency, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - New York University Medical Center, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Photograph of woman and dog, inscribed on verso: "Mac et moi," snapshot, 1983 Jul (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Resumes and biographical material, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    An electronic file with Whitmore's "authors' questionnaire" is available through Access Services: Disk #43, file GROVE.BIO
    An electronic file that lists Whitmore's freelance clients is available through Access Services: Disk #43, file RESUME
  - Whitmore family, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Yaddo, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Computer manuals and documentation, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
    Includes user notes and four published manuals
- Writings: Fiction, 1959-1989; Series II; 2.71; (8 boxes)
  Organized into four subseries: Novels; Plays; Poetry; and Short Stories.
  The series covers Whitmore's creative writings, and holds manuscripts, typescripts, printed versions, clippings, correspondence and contracts, with some research materials.
  The first subseries holds files on Whitmore's four novels. The earliest, The Elysium Fire, was a fictionalized work centering on the tragic 1977 fire at the Everard Baths in New York. He did not find a publisher for it, though the Village Voice did print his investigative piece on the fire; a file on that article appears in Series III, and his Everard Baths research files are held in Series V. Whitmore's first published novel, The Confessions of Danny Slocum (St. Martin's Press, 1980) was expanded from a short story that had appeared in the magazine Christopher Street the year before; it was also issued as a paperback (Grey Fox Press, 1985) and optioned for a film. Similarly, his later novel Nebraska (Grove Press, 1987; reprint, Washington Square Press, 1989) had its beginnings as play. The fourth work, Deep Dish, was serialized in the New York Native newspaper between 1980 and 1982.
  The Plays subseries contains material on eight of his works for the stage, though only three, The Caseworker, The Rights, and Two Plays for Three Women: Flight/The Legacy, appear to have been produced; the latter piece is about Gertrude Stein.
  The Poetry subseries begins with a set of chronologically-grouped poems that had been arranged by Whitmore in dated folders, followed by specifically-grouped pieces and individual works. Many of the poems were self-published, such as those in his "Getting Gay in New York" series: they appeared in several periodicals as well as in various compilations issued by Whitmore's own Free Milk Fund Press. Some of those presentations have decorated paper covers, while others are simply enclosed in commercial pressboard binders. In addition, Whitmore recorded a set of the poems for the use of the blind, and a copy of that audio tape is filed here. His "Cripple Creek" series, supported by a New York State CAPS grant, makes reference to the history of his home state of Colorado, and those files include research material, largely newspaper clippings, related to events mentioned in the poems. At the end of the subseries is a folder of promotional ephemera and correspondence documenting public poetry readings that Whitmore gave between 1972 and 1983, as well as a folder of loose and miscellaneous poems that had been filed with the ephemera. Mostly reproductions but with some original typescripts, they may be the copies from which he read during his appearances.
  The Short Stories subseries holds nearly fifty of Whitmore's stories, very few of which appear to have been published. For the most part they are undated; those carrying the date "before 1967" were together in a folder labeled as such by Whitmore. As that is the year of his graduation from MacMurray College, they are likely stories he submitted to high school or college publications; many of these papers have comments, mostly "yes" or "no" with jurors' initials. The story "Bearing Arms" was typed on the verso of copies of his resume and original pages of an unidentified play script.
  At the end of the subseries is a bound group of independent tales that Whitmore saw as a "set piece" titled "Out Here: Fire Island Tales." The binder bears Patricia Russell-Loud's paper label and holds photocopies of six stories; the typescripts and printed versions of the same stories are filed alphabetically following the binder. Whitmore's introduction to the bound set lists the other stories that were "in the works" but they are not present among his papers.
  - Novels
    - Confessions of Danny Slocum
      - Short story published in Christopher Street
        - Contract and correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 26)
        - Typescript, photocopy, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 27)
        - Typescript, photocopy, edited, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
        - Galley and edits, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 30)
        - Magazine issue (3 copies), 1979 Jul (Box 3, Folder 31)
        - Fan mail, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - St. Martin's Press edition
        - Contract, correspondence, royalty statements, 1979-1984 (Box 3, Folder 33)
        - Typescript, corrected, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 34-37)
        - Reviews, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
        - Fan mail, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Grey Fox Press edition
        - Contract and correspondence, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 41)
        - Reviews, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Film rights agreement and correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Deep Dish, 1980-1982
      - Episodes 1-29, typescripts, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 44-46)
      - Parts 1-18 and 20-26, printed versions, 1980-1982
    - The Elysium Fire, typescript photocopy, and correspondence with prospective publishers, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 47-50)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Whitmore's Village Voice article on the Baths is in Series III, Box 12, folder 171
      See also research materials in Series V, box 16, folders 236-236
    - Nebraska
      See also: electronic files for drafts of this novel available through Access Services: Disks #13-15 and #24-26
      See also: files on the play "Nebraska," box 5, folders 63-64
      - Rejection letters, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - Contract, correspondence, photographs, map, 1959-1989 (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - Galleys, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 53-54)
      - Reviews, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Fan mail, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Plays
    - "As I Lay Dying: a screenplay," mimeograph, before 1972 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - "Beloved Intruder: A Radio Movie," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - The Caseworker
      - Copyright certificate, production papers, photographs, review, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 59)
      - Script, typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - Script, typescript photocopy, undated (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - Stage designs, 1976
    - Memory, typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Nebraska, scripts (2), photocopies, one with corrections, undated (Box 5, Folder 63-64)
      See also: Nebraska novel files in Box 4, folders 51-56
    - Photo Real
      - Audio recording of script reading, 57:41 minutes (1 of 2), March 19; 1; 00:20:14 (Box 5, Item barcode 39002091396979)
        Features Whitmore reading scene introductions
      - Audio recording of script reading (2 of 2), March 19; 1; 00:37:58; There is static and high background noise on the tape. (Box 5, Item barcode 39002091396987)
      - Script, typescript photocopy, undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - The Rights
      - Audio recording of play rehearsal or performance, 58:39 minutes, 1971 September 6; 1; 00:59:35; There is high background noise and static on the tape. (Box 5, Item barcode 39002091396995)
      - Production notes, programs, fan mail, photographs, 1980, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 68)
      - Script, typescript photocopy, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - Script, typescript, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 70)
      - Script, typescript photocopy with director's annotations, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 71)
      - Poster, review, 1980, 1983
    - Secretaries: Two Comedies, typescript photocopy, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Two Plays for Three Women: Flight/The Legacy
      - Script, typescript and photocopy, annotated, with programs and advertisement, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 73)
      - Review, feature article, 1979
  - Poetry
    - Poems, typescripts, before 1967 (Box 7, Folder 74)
    - Poems, typescripts, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 75)
    - Poems, typescripts, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 76)
    - Poems, typescripts, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 77)
    - Poems, typescripts, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 78)
    - Poems, typescripts and typescript photocopies, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 79)
    - "As In Stendhal," published in Christopher Street, with typescript and photocopy, 1977 Oct, undated (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - "Cripple Creek" series
      - Poems in binder, photocopies, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 81)
      - Three Poems from "Cripple Creek", published by Free Milk Fund Press, printed version, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 82)
      - Research and reference material, undated (Box 7, Folder 83)
    - "Getting Gay In New York" series
      - Selection of twenty poems, typescript and photocopy (in binders), undated (Box 7, Folder 84)
      - Selection of forty poems, photocopy (in binder), undated (Box 7, Folder 85)
      - Eighteen Poems from Getting Gay in New York, and other poems, published by Free Milk Fund Press, printed version (2 copies), 1973 (Box 7, Folder 86)
      - Getting Gay in New York, and other poems, published by Free Milk Fund Press, printed version, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 87)
      - Selections of one and three poems, in Fag Rag, printed versions, 1974, 1975
      - Getting Gay in New York, published by Free Milk Fund Press, printed version (3 copies), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 88)
      - Selections published in "...writings about ourselves," printed version, undated (Box 7, Folder 89)
      - Letter from Martin Duberman, with extra sheets of poems, 1973, 1976, undated (Box 7, Folder 90)
      - Audio recording, 1980 August 5; 1; 00:27:50; There is static on the tape. (Box 7, Item barcode 39002091397001)
        Poems read by Whitmore; "recorded solely for the use of the blind" by Gay and Lesbian New York
      - Reviews, 1976-1978
    - "In the Fall of States," broadside poem published by Free Milk Fund Press, printed version, 1979
    - "Malcombe: a prose poem," printed version from unidentified publication, undated (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - "Natural History," electronic file, undated